And her first class is "Intergalactic Revolutionaries and You," and America is so excited, she's ready to show off her strength, she's ready to show off her portal-punching skills, (Laughter) and I stripped that safety net from her right away. And I limited her powers, and I changed up her location and shook up her world, because that is what college is like, (Laughter) especially if you're alone. But I didn't want America to be alone for long, and so in a homework assignment gone totally wrong, she lands on a battlefield with the X-Men. (Laughter) Because, when I was in college, the Reverend Kelly Brown Douglas was my mentor, and I knew that America Chavez needed one, too. And who better to mentor America Chavez than Storm, the first black female superhero and one of the most powerful members of the X-Men? Nobody, that's who. (Laughter) And Storm teaches America how to quiet her mind inside of a star portal, and when America quiets her mind, she opens up the dimensions, and in that silence, she can listen for anything and anyone. And no one has ever offered her silence and deep reflection as a way to be powerful. And at first, she rejects it, but with Storm's encouragement, it clicks, and America quiets the world around her, and she leans into a deep vulnerability. I mean, her and Storm even hug. I know. And that's because my mentors loved me enough to encourage me to investigate myself and my ancestors, and when you're 19, how do you even know what that means? I didn't learn about the history of my people in college. I learned about the history of my people sitting on my grandmother's lap when she pulled out the photo album and she named everyone that was here and everyone still left on the island. So obviously, I had to crash-land a grandma on America Chavez, and not just any grandma -- a big, strong, luchador grandma, one that loved her enough to take her to the ancestral plain, where America Chavez could see the history of her people play out in the skies above. And America gets to see Planeta Fuertona, the birth planet of her grandmother, and she sees it get invaded, and she sees her grandmother and her mom flee. And she also sees the joy that they experience when their new homeland accepts them openly and offers them tremendous care. She gets to see great pain met with even greater compassion, and that's right alongside the tremendous strength of her family. And so everywhere that I could, right, I wrote her little love notes for her and for all the other queer kids of color trying to be magnificent. Like, when you lose yourself, dig deep into your ancestry, because you will find the pieces there. And also, reminders that soft is not a pass to duck, to hide, to be silent, to cower. Soft is also a push to hold ourselves accountable. Kind of like when America lands in World War II and comes face-to-face with Hitler, and she knocks him the hell out ... (Laughter) just like Captain America did in 1941, and who knew we'd need America Chavez to punch Nazis in 2018. (Laughter) (Applause) And even that, that justified act kind of wrecks her a little bit, so I made sure that she linked up with her best friend, and they talk feelings and they go on a road trip and they sing "Just a Girl" by No Doubt at the top of their lungs. (Laughter) And when Midas, a sinister corporation, takes control of Sotomayor, threatens to ban portals and almost kills America ... her ancestors reach for her ... because they know that she needs to heal. And it is that burst of care, that healing, that gives her the fuel to defeat Midas and reclaim herself. See, because that myth of having to go it alone and having to be tough ... doesn't serve us. America Chavez is a whole superhero, and she still needed a team of support to help her find herself. And she needed that gentleness, the type of gentleness that is rooted in compassion and still very much invested in justice and liberation. Because it's in that space where softness and vulnerability meet strength that we transcend our everyday selves, that we become something greater, something majestic, maybe even something super. Thank you. (Applause)
Y su primera clase fue "Los revolucionarios intergalácticos y tú" y América estaba tan emocionada que estaba lista para mostrar su poder: su habilidad para abrir portales a golpes; (Risas) pero inmediatamente le quité ese mecanismo de protección. Limité sus poderes, la mudé a otro sitio, y sacudí su mundo porque eso es lo que ocurre en la universidad, (Risas) sobre todo si estás sola. Pero no quise que América estuviera sola por mucho tiempo, así que gracias a una tarea que le salió mal, termina en un campo de batalla con los X-Men. (Risas) Porque cuando yo estaba en la universidad, mi mentor fue el reverendo Kelly Brown Douglas, y allí supe que América Chávez también necesitaría uno. ¿Y quién podría ser un mejor mentor para América Chávez que Tormenta, la primera superheroína negra y uno de los miembros más poderosos de los X-Men? Nadie, solo ella. (Risas) Tormenta le enseña a América a calmar su mente dentro de un portal estelar, y cuando América lo logra, consigue abrir otras dimensiones, y en ese silencio puede escucharlo todo y a todos. Nadie le había enseñado que el silencio y la reflexión profunda eran una forma de poder. Al principio lo rechaza, pero con la motivación de Tormenta lo consigue, y América logra silenciar el mundo que la rodea, y se deja envolver por una profunda vulnerabilidad. ¡Hasta llega abraza a Tormenta! Genial. Y eso fue gracias a mis mentores, que me quisieron lo suficiente para incentivarme a descubrirme a mí misma y a mis ancestros. Cuando tienes 19 años, ¿cómo sabes siquiera lo que significa eso? La historia de mi gente no la aprendí en la universidad. La historia de mi gente la aprendí sentada en el regazo de mi abuela cuando sacaba el álbum de fotos y nombraba a todos los que estaban aquí y a los que se quedaron en la isla. Así que a América Chávez, le tenía que llegar de sorpresa una abuela, aunque no una abuela cualquiera... sino una abuela luchadora, grande y fuerte, una que la amara tanto que la llevara al Plano Ancestral donde América Chávez viera la historia de su gente proyectada en el cielo. Y América llega a ver al Planeta Fuertona, el planeta donde nació su abuela, y ve cuando el planeta es invadido, y luego ve a su abuela y a su madre cuando huyen. También ve la alegría que sintieron cuando un nuevo hogar las recibió con los brazos abiertos y les ofreció muchísimo cariño. América vio que frente al dolor recibieron una gran compasión, junto a la gran fuerza de su familia. Así que cada vez que pude, le dejé pequeñas notas de afecto para ella y para todos los otros jóvenes 'queer' de color que tratan de ser fabulosos. Como cuando te sientes perdido, buscas dentro del pasado de tu familia y allí conseguirás las respuestas. También recuerda que el no ser fuerte no te da derecho a aislarte, esconderte, callarte o acobardarte. El no ser fuerte también nos empuja a ser responsables. Como cuando América llega a la Segunda Guerra Mundial, y se encuentra frente a frente con Hitler y le da una golpiza de las buenas... (Risas) así como el Capitán América lo hizo en 1941, y quién diría que América Chávez continuaría combatiendo nazis en el 2018. (Risas) (Aplausos) Y aun cuando ese acto justificado la afecta un poco, así que quise que se conectara con su mejor amiga para hablar de sus sentimientos, y juntas viajan por la carretera y a todo pulmón cantan "Just a Girl" de No Doubt . (Risas) Y cuando Midas, una empresa siniestra que toma el control de Sotomayor amenaza cerrar los portales y casi mata a América... sus ancestros se conectan con ella porque saben que los necesita para sanar. Y es ese cariño, esa sanación, lo que le da la energía para vencer a Midas y recuperarse. Porque ese mito de que tienes que enfrentarlo sola y tienes que ser fuerte... no funciona. América Chávez es una verdadera supeheroína pero aun así necesita un equipo que la apoye para encontrarse a sí misma. Y ella necesitaba de esa ternura, el tipo de ternura que está enraizada en la compasión, y está conectada con la justicia y la liberación. Es en ese espacio donde la vulnerabilidad, la debilidad y la fuerza se encuentran donde logramos trascender y convertirnos en algo mucho mejor, algo majestuoso e incluso, algo súper. Gracias. (Aplausos)